BRIAN MONTANA

703 W Wellington Ave, Chicago, IL 60657 708 220 8860 | contact@brianmontana.net

SUMMARY

Experienced software engineer with 3 years of management experience, delivering complex projects with a successful track record in optimizing performance, and driving innovation across multiple organizations. Strong leadership and management skills, with a focus on fostering collaboration, mentoring teams, and implementing continuous improvements for enhanced organizational effectiveness and customer satisfaction.

EXPERIENCE

MVMNT Chicago, IL

<u>Senior Software Engineer</u>

January 2023 - Present

- Expanded testing capabilities across 7 microservices and the UI with a comprehensive framework employing MSW and Playwright for E2E and integration tests, along with regression tests on services, views, and components.
- Implemented GitHooks for faster developer feedback to revamp the CI/CD flow, and ensured the QA of over 50% of engineering tasks aligned with acceptance criteria boosting software engineering performance and throughput.
- Set up a concerted effort to preserve and expand customer feedback, reduce reported bugs, and safeguard revenue-driving features for software platform with a 24 hour resolution
- Created and architected PDF generation, image management, UI for complex data management over, restructured UX for logo and document upload, and contributed to enrichment of other product features catering to customer needs.
- Conducted 4 instructing sessions for an 18-member engineering team from OpenAPI's TypeScript code generation to architecture
 of BFF solution of 7 Kotlin microservices.

UNITEDHEALTH GROUP (RALLY HEALTH)

Chicago, IL

Engineering Manager

January 2021 – December 2022

- Achieved improvement of login flow for a web platform supporting 15mn users by reducing login speed by 16%, coordinated with 24+ teams and senior executives.
- Managed implementation of a feature for Covid-19 vaccines, and medical information driving 40K unique users in five weeks and generated an 800% increase over original projections.
- Trained 12 engineers on UI development principles to minimize learning curve for new hires, provide coaching, and mentorship to transfer skills and knowledge.
- Served as emergency contact to triage, facilitate, and resolve issues related to deployment process during production releases over a 2-week period managing 12 services leveraged by over 15mn users to minimize down time.

<u>Engineering Lead</u> February 2020 – January 2021

- Spearheaded an effort to improve accessibility, WCAG 2.1 and WCAG 2.0 score, by 22% from previous year to ~90% compliance.
- Directed a team of 6 engineers; delegated responsibilities, provided coaching, defined workflows, and conducted performance evaluations resulting in 3 promotions.
- Ensured web application trimmed business expenses by \$4.2M per year, increased scalability and enhanced efficiency by computerizing customer service experience.
- Orchestrated creation of a data generation tool to automate onboarding process for new consumers decrease developer utilization by 30% per request.
- Restructured testing performance, quality, and coverage for web application by cutting down feedback loop by up to 60%.

<u>Senior Software Engineer</u>

July 2019 – January 2020

• Fostered a platform with 40K daily active users, redefined processes to streamline new hire onboarding, and introduced a process to debug frontend local code in higher environments.

PUBLICIS GROUPE (CONVERSANT LLC)

Chicago, IL

Senior Front-End Engineer

March 2018 - July 2019

- Created and developed an email platform for serving over 1B emails a month with a data platform on a team of six developers,
 mitigated partner dependency for QA and development by 50% and time to launch for client requests by 16%.
- Spearheaded creation of a modern Adobe extension architecture leveraging latest technology and development methodologies, decreased manual development steps, mitigated environment crashes, and access to current web APIs.

- Refactored a feature by 62.5% of its compiled file size, cut down memory use, applied object-oriented methodologies, and consolidated four implementations.
- Simplified a feature's codebase by 30%, compiling time from 22 seconds to 1.5 second, and testing time for new features with automated linting, testing, and Git hooks.

WUNDERMAN (BLAST RADIUS)

Chicago, IL

Senior Interface Developer

August 2016 - February 2018

• Built, constructed, and prototyped a UI utilizing JavaScript, CSS, and HTML to update an ecommerce and client digital platform projects for clients worth up to \$4M.

CLOSERLOOK, INC

Chicago, IL

Interactive Developer

February 2015 – July 2016

Constructed a UI framework, utilized modern technologies and processes on a team of 22 to improved ease of use, maintenance, construction, and lower average project time by 60%.

BLUE CHIP MARKETING WORLDWIDE

Northbrook, IL

Front End Developer

June 2013 – January 2015

• Designed, built, and maintained 25 websites for clients including Proctor & Gamble, PrimeSource, Fisher Nuts, Merck, Ricola, Alvine, and Blue Bunny, on a team of 20.

EDUCATION

THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO BOOTH SCHOOL OF BUSINESS

Chicago, IL

Master of Business Administration

March 2023 – Present

NORTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY

Dekalb, IL

Master of Fine Arts, New Media

September 2010 - May 2013

VOLUNTEERISM

CODE PLATOON

Chicago, IL

Mentor and Ambassador

January 2019 - Present

• Mentored, facilitated, and trained 6 veterans' professional development for transitioning into software engineering with 83% employed after 6 months as software engineers.

COMPUTER.ART (CODEPEN CHICAGO)

Chicago, IL

Organizer

January 2017 – Present

• Organized creative coding events with 500+ members, and 50 in attendance with 5-10 presenters at each event sponsored by over 10 companies.

ADDITIONAL

- Software Engineering: Angular, TypeScript, React, Vue, Webpack, HTML, C, CSS, A11Y, JavaScript, MySQL, Node, Prototyping, Responsive Design, Design, UX, E2E Testing, Mono repo, ADR (Architectural Decision Record), RFC (Review for Comments), Svelte, Scala, Java, PHP, Python, Kotlin, Jenkins, BASH, CI/CD, Playwright, Datadog, Groovy, GitHub, Docker, Jira, Git, Splunk, Slack
- Management: Coaching, mentoring, technical, collaboration, compliance, project management, innovation, communication, delivery.